[SPEAKER_01]: This is from the Anguttara Nikaya, a sutta called Walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Walking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh, it just says, if a sensual thought or thought of ill-will or cruelty arises while walking, and if you tolerate it and do not abandon it, then you are devoid of effort and moral shame, constantly lazy and lacking energy while walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it goes on, whether walking, standing, sitting or lying down, one who thinks bad thoughts, connected with household life, has entered upon the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infatuated by delusive things, such a person cannot be free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one who has his thoughts calmed and delights in stilling of thought, such a person can be free.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a lot of walking meditation out there, people like to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's... they focus on the feeling of their feet on the sand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the actual nature of the thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's quite common.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, you know, walk from this point to that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: How many steps?
[SPEAKER_01]: 30 steps?
[SPEAKER_00]: Same for anybody posture, when they're sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when the Buddha says he's upon the wrong path, means he's going down the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means in the most accurate manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, going down the wrong path, it's basically attending to things wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means going down the wrong direction of your... of your efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even the ones who are making the efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the example you gave.
[SPEAKER_00]: When... when you're doing walking meditation, mostly today people, again, they're after... you're after an experience of peace or some... some sort of... some sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no factual... well, you're after experience of peace, or some sort of experience, or some novelty, or the other, but... not many people would use the meditation to reflect upon the nature of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that's all this is to talk about, as anything that really matters, is to not entertain the unwholesome, and to cultivate the wholesome, whether you're sitting, walking, lying down, or standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're talking, whether you're alone or with people.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, unfortunately, today, you get this, like a mass group retreat centers and so on, and then you get taught, like, walking meditation, you observe the soles of your feet and you try to, like, be as present as possible and catch the moment and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that is nothing other than just a focusing practice on a particular aspect of your body, on a particular, basically, type of perception, of touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can be so... it can... it can produce a release for people, because most of the... most of the... rest of the... rest of the time, they spend... they spend their... their day in an unmindful state, very busy, very engaged, and then just focusing on one particular thing and refusing to give attention to everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seems like a way to go, because it provides you with a degree of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that peace is only relative to your lifestyle beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: That peace is not the measure of your understanding and wisdom that comes if you do the dhamma correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not a hard thing to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just see when you're out of the retreat, how much of your composure you can keep when you go back to your daily life, to your other things, dealing with things, whether you'll still be able to remain impenetrable to the unwholesome states as you're walking, sitting, lying down or standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most people won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they have to go back for retreats, prolonging retreats, doing longer retreats, more intense retreats, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they say, if I focus on my feet, walking on the sand, then I don't think any sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where you focus is not the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of the problem is not understanding the nature of unwholesome, and because of that, being subject to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't know how, even unwittingly, you entertain it, you fuel it, you feed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you end up acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think of unwholesome thoughts as a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, proliferating unwholesome thoughts are a further problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what happens when people do the focusing practice, they would focus on one particular thing and refuse to give attention to everything else, including the problem, the problem of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then they can feel like, yeah, this is really working.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I mean, I'm not saying there's absolutely, like, no benefit whatsoever, but I'm saying the benefit is only relative for those who are distracted most of the other time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Distracted with duty, with family, with sensuality, or just with your views, in some cases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is to recognize that, like, yeah, not giving attention to the problem can help you, but that's not solving the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just managing it, dealing with it temporarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can practice and further this type of focusing meditation only in such retreat settings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't sustain that out in the world, or you can't sustain that if you have to climb up and down the mountain every single day for Pindapar for five kilometers in rain or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can try, but you're going to burn out very soon.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you see many, many, many cases that, well, we both kind of witnessed, with the monks who would go in the great seclusion, focused on some sort of technique to do it, and then just after a week or two, you can't handle it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need some reference point, because, okay, now you stopped attending.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just focusing on one thing, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a wall.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a dead end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only benefit you were getting before, from your meditation practice, wasn't because of what you were focusing on, it's because of what you were not focusing on, which was the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were not focusing on unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the peace you were getting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you arrived and not focusing on a wholesome, because you're focusing on something else, which sooner or later, environment will prevent you to do so, or you're just going to run out of the of the most obvious inspiration to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what you're going to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just back in the same unwholesome, which remain intact, because you haven't been understanding it, discerning it, resolving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've been ignoring it, through watching the soles of your feet, through watching the tip of your nose, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody denies that people can experience peaceful feelings when they do focusing meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point here is that won't result in uprooting the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only approve the problem if you start looking at it for what it is, directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the part of the sutta you read just talks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: The work is not about me doing walking meditation for eight hours a day, or focusing on my nostrils all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: The work is recognizing whether the mind is affected by ill-will, affected by greed, affected by delusion, affected by unwholesome states, and then not entertaining that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter whether I'm walking, sitting, lying down, or standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: What posture?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the posture is your reference point that you don't need to interfere with, if you know where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the problem is mind affected by unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, indeed, sometimes, when it's just too much to deal with, yeah, just ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just don't pay any attention to it until it calms down, so that you can go back to it and deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But
[SPEAKER_00]: Adopting a practice of just constantly not looking at the problem and focusing on something else, as a way of release from the problem, it's not going to resolve anything, because there's absolutely no discernment there, no wisdom, no understanding, because you're not looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why... that's why the Buddha did say, when he gave that simile, he says,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being free... not being free from sensuality, these samanas and brāhmaṇas, they pre-meditate, mis-meditate, over-meditate, under-meditate, but they don't meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it gives a simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says they are like... like an owl hunting for a mouse, or a cat waiting to pounce on a fish, or... or... or... or... similes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, similes of preying upon something, of focusing on one moment where you act, where you catch it, where you grab it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, that's meditating with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's looking completely down the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, again, just imagine yourself preying upon something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're waiting for, I don't know, a mouse to come out of this hole.
[SPEAKER_00]: You mustn't skip a beat, because he might escape you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see whether that's different from when people try to not skip a beat when they're observing the soles of their feet, or not skip a beat when they're focusing on the nostrils, or the belly movement, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up cultivating the same attitude of preying upon something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Preying upon something that you clearly think has value.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to resolve all your problems.
[SPEAKER_00]: Catching this mouse will fix all my problems.
[SPEAKER_00]: Catching these perfect moments that come and go in front of me will purify my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a completely...
[SPEAKER_00]: He said people who meditate like that, meditate with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they pre-meditate, mis-meditate, over-meditate, under-meditate and so on, but they don't meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you walk in, a thought of cruelty arises, and they don't tolerate it, which means... Yeah, which means you don't... like... thought of cruelty arises, means... there's your work then for you, in its entirety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't... you don't stop everything you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't... you... like... just give it all up, because I will never...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want ever to have such thoughts again.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't do that, because... well, it's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those thoughts will be presented themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order for you to not be victim of those presentations of ill-will or sensuality, you need to understand how you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't understand the habits of your engagement with those thoughts, while they're simultaneously present there, if your sole response to that is look away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just look away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... just concentrate on my breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Concentrate on my breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on top of that, you're going to wind yourself up much more, because thinking that you must stop thinking, is another thought, that you're thinking, in order to not think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it becomes so intense and sort of unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize the thought of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, that's enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very often.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, your recognition might not be clear enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you need to endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to recognize whereby... how much of the thought arises on its own, and then you have to recognize where the... where the line is, where if you cross, then it's you doing it, you entertaining it, you getting involved with it, you trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those are ways of fueling the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including you actively trying to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would... like, there is a thought in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must focus on my soles of my feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're trying to avoid the arisen thought in your mind that you think you must not have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by trying to avoid things that are disagreeable to you, what are you doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing exactly the thing you shouldn't be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting out of craving in regard to how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must have it longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must have it longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a recognition that this is a cruel thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The cruel thought presented itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a cruel thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a cruel thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like somebody comes right here in front of your door.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is a public space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your kuti is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't come in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they have every right to stand in front of your kuti.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you feel affected by that, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you come out of your kuti and start to chase them, well, now you actually went into something that's not your domain, not your ownership, and trying to control it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then means you left kuti unattended, and then other things can come in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're everywhere and nowhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same, in the same manner, the thing cannot come in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever thought is, unless you invite it in, unless you drag it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what happens with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either sensuality, as in like agreeable desire, or disagreeable, something you want to get rid of, it just comes in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's agreeable, you are the one who brings it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's disagreeable, you are the one who goes out and tries to chase it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you overstep your boundary.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you're subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you're affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's that another sutta where the Buddha did say, while he was still unenlightened bodhisattva, when he was in the... it's called fear and dread, nājā-mikāya.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he said, he'd be staying in this frightening forest and groves with wild animals, and then he'd be doing walking meditation at night.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, if there is a... if he would hear some sound or something, or have a frightening thought,
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't change what he was doing, which is walking with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't stop walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't stop walking until he dispels that unwholesome state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he might change the posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same manner, whether he was seated, standing, sitting or lying down, he wouldn't change the posture before... unless he first removed the unwholesome state that had arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you remove the unwholesome state,
[SPEAKER_00]: By not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not trying to prolong it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't change the posture until this state is dispelled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if the unwholesome state came up, and now he stopped walking and done something else, means he acted out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already a way of fueling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you acted out of it in a form of trying to prolong it, as in unwholesome state of sensuality, or trying to deny it, get rid of it as quickly as possible, as in unwholesome state of ill will, or fear, or anything disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, you recognize, and then, how much of it arises on its own, and then, you don't either add to it, or take away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it subsides, then you change the posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you do that long enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do that long enough, any... no matter how subtle ways of fueling the unwholesome states of your mind you've been entertaining, they will all fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you just... you're uprooting it left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bit by bit by bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can uproot things, but it takes time for them to sort of wither and die.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one thing for sure, they'll never wither and die, and you certainly never uprooted them, if you keep looking elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you keep focusing on your nostrils for the sake of avoiding the thought and not having to think about anything and not having to experience displeasure, if you keep focusing on the soles of your feet because you're trying to catch a perfect moment and develop this ultimate peace, they will never be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The non-disturbance doesn't come from not experiencing disturbing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-disturbance comes from not being disturbed by the disturbing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as you're concerned with disturbing things, not with your response in regard to disturbing things, you're looking in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are down the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something to do, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're focused on doing things, staring at things, perceiving things, observing things, but not looking your attitude behind that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The intentionality behind, the motivation behind, the craving behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is always behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always in regard to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you never look in that direction of that background, you're never going to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, there's these ideas that, by being in a particular posture, cross-legged, lotus position, back straight, spine erect, loosened, loose belly, all these posturings,
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't do the work for you, but that is a game that you play.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a little ritual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Little motions you go through to create the significance of what you're about to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you just sit down, stare at the wall, or look down the hill, and contemplate, why do you suffer when you can't fulfill your desires?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or why do you suffer when you experience something disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you suffer when you're paired with things you don't want?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you suffer when you're separated from things you want?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's not much to it that you can perform.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's for many people, it's almost just abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they need something more palpable, which is on a level of sort of mechanical performance, doing things with your body, particular posture, particular way of walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must be stepping on the outsides of my soles or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't be walking like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must walk slowly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't walk fast.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is being concerned with a particular... with a particular content of your perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see the nature behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certainly, failing to recognize the enduring feeling in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, athletic meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: How long do you sit?
[SPEAKER_01]: Two hours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Some guys can sit for two weeks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's all based, as I said, it all revolves around trying to perceive, trying to catch, preying upon something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you would have to go through these specialized motions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you walk too fast, you can't be catching something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you must walk slowly, slow down, stand, stand, and just look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, just, just grab it as it comes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognize it, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's nothing else than meditating with that same sensuality that you're trying to overcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there's no... no unwholesome thoughts arising, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: If no unwholesome... well, then you're either an arahant, or you don't know what unwholesome thoughts are, so you think they're not arising while they're fully there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be the third option.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ask yourself, am I an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there are unwholesome thoughts, which means I need to look harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or change the criteria for what constitutes a wholesome thought, unwholesome thought for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because having a peaceful experience... That doesn't mean that it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peaceful experience is unwholesome, if you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, not ultimately unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not unwholesome on the level of raging sensuality or mad ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from the point of view of ultimate, complete, thorough liberation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no full understanding, to that degree, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The neutral feeling, the most sublime feeling, praised by the wise, it's unwholesome if it's not known.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's wholesome if it's known.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a constant knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no constant knowledge, in a sense of all-knowing, all the time, in every direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowledge in regard to the horizon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we talk about knowledge of arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: The constant knowledge of the arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Constant knowledge in regard to arising, it's other way of saying wisdom, in regard to dhammas, in regard to things that manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wisdom stays.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if you develop wisdom in regard to nature of things, that wisdom stays.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is always... things are always present in one way or the other, which means wisdom in regard to them, it's always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully developed principle, like that, is what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regenerating wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's simultaneously arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever it's manifested, that is wisely understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its nature has been fully abandoned, disregarded, in a sense of no appropriation, no assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Because you cannot have things arising for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're just locked in some... buried in some cave without any perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, dhammas are right in front of you all the time, as you thought, as absence of sights, absence of sounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are real manifesting things, as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as the five aggregates are there functioning, there is the five aggregates of phenomena, the five aggregates of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how much of a content within that you might have or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why trying to avoid sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, that would compare that to a blind and a deaf man,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to somebody who's developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, you avoid the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't engage with the unwholesome sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't entertain them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just replacing one very unwholesome content with not unwholesome content.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to be free from either, you need to fully understand the nature of that content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't get there just by staring at the content and expecting content to tell you what its nature is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that would mean people could almost accidentally stumble upon enlightenment, just by staring and suddenly they get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to develop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In another sutra, in Anguttara Nikaya, the Buddha's talking to Anuruddha, one of his disciples, he says, this dhamma is for one with few desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for one with strong desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: With reference to what was this said, it says, when a bhikkhu is one with few desires, he does not desire, let people know me, to be one with few desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he is content, he does not desire that people know me to be one who is content.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he resorts to solitude, he does not desire that people know me to be one who resorts to solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he is energetic, he does not desire that people know me to be energetic.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he is mindful, he does not want people to know that he is mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he is composed, he does not want people to know that he is composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when he is wise, he does not want people to know that he is wise.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he delights in non-proliferation, he does not desire that people know me to be one who delights in non-proliferation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this dhamma is for one with few desires, but with strong desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not seeking fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it's more... it's more fundamental than just the fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down to...
[SPEAKER_00]: See, all of the things that Buddha listed are wholesome things.
[SPEAKER_00]: A few desires, solitude, mindfulness, wisdom, restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's almost like a...
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire can be also reflexive.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't necessarily need to be focused on the central content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can be practicing renunciation in the forest and stuff, but then, on the reflexive manner, you can be... well, you can be developing a tribe, a country, a conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be indulging that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you really want your practice to make a difference to yourself, you need to practice on both of those levels, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you need to be mindful of the motivation behind your practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if... say you want to go in the remote forest, but the motivation behind it is because the word will spread around that you go out in the remote forests, so you'll be, yeah, famous or simply conceited.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll experience pleasure on account of other knowing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that doesn't mean you shouldn't go to the forest, because going to the forest is still wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you go to a forest, if you go to a forest, you make the effort to re-root.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, the Buddha encouraged, when it comes down to eating, we can't just stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you eat with right motivation, then it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't eat with right motivation, then it's automatically unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean, if you cannot eat with right motivation, you must stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just must work harder to be able to re-root the reasons for your eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: To root them in wholesome, not root them in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, you recognize, firstly, what is it that you're about to do, and then, secondly, why.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I want to go and keep all the dhūtanghas and live in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would sometimes say, let those who want to go and live on the root of truth, live on the root of truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let those who want to eat once a day, eat once a day or eat out of their bowl.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not everybody must do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because some people won't be able to help it, but do it out of conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of pride.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of, I can sit motionless for 10 hours and I eat only once every three days.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like giants, they started out doing each other in their practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who's going to go further?
[SPEAKER_00]: Harder asceticism.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, no second layer of that reflection I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just focus on doing these things that are deemed right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they bringing the unwholesome to decrease and increasing wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just winding you up stronger and stronger in your desire for fame or recognition or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, asceticism is almost always good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you really want to make it beneficial, you have to then look at another step back and see why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, not necessarily dismiss it, if you find that it's done for wrong reasons, but change the reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't change the reasons for unwholesome action, like sensuality, for example, or anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't say, oh, I'll reroute that in good.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those things are cemented in unwholesome motivation, always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motivation of ignorance, lust, aversion, which means you must just abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there are many things, such as eating, or even practicing, going to the forest, and so on, that you can make unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: There can be some people who live in a monastery, and because they're surrounded by others,
[SPEAKER_01]: They become quite ascetic, quite, you know, many practices ascetic by sitting for many hours each and every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as soon as they go and live by themselves, all those practices are gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means they haven't been taking responsibility from the practice, for the practice, from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've been relying on the temple environment, other monks around them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what kept them in check.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, once you're out of that setting, you just... well, you dissolve.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, even if it's not explicitly for their acknowledgement, you do it... you do it basically not with your own... taking on responsibility on yourself, but you do it because the environment, everybody does it, and if you don't do it, you stand out too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily a bad way to start.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you recognize it, that's only a starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, adhering to the environment and never changing it, for the sake of the value of the environment in itself, means, how do you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you know where your motivation is rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: And on top of it, it can't possibly be good for you being surrounded by the people, even if it's other monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said... well, actually, it's very, very close to what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Going to a solitude is always wholesome in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, you can make it unwholesome, but you can undo that bit and still go to solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that sutta where the Buddha said if a monk lives in the forest and he's lazy, sleeps all the time, thinks about sensuality, but he still stays in the forest,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, sooner or later, the mind will calm down, get used to the perceptions of the forest, and he'll abandon those unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is the benefit of the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, counterpart to that monk is the monk who lives in a temple, frequented by lay people, not far from the town or the villages, surrounded by other monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: He lives there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if he's not spending his time thinking about sensuality, even if he's not lazy, even if he's not negligent, he will become so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the environment of the crowd and other people, that's what's going to result into.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, you can benefit from it initially, but not as a fixed in stone sort of principle that you must always be with 30 other monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you must always be like within the stone's throw away from the town or the village.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the contrary.
[SPEAKER_00]: You read the suttas, you know, empty huts, empty forests, empty roots of the trees.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you waiting for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can... people can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't want to deal with any of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll run into the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's done for unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if they stay in that forest, they will have to correct those reasons or they will leave the forest and this road.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, the environment does... well, does direct... direct basically... direct you in your practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter of your restraint and diligence and everything else, if you live surrounded by others constantly, you cannot progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is another point that says that this dhamma is for one who resorts to solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for one who delights in company.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, resorting to solitude means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual physical solitude doesn't mean going to your bedroom and closing the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: This goes on further.
[SPEAKER_01]: When a bhikkhu resorts to solitude, bhikkhus, bhikkhunis, male lay followers, female lay followers, kings, royal ministers, and so on, approaching, in each case, with a mind that slants, slopes and climbs to seclusion, withdrawn,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not encouraging or entertaining them to stay any longer, because you don't want them there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want them there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you go even further, like you often end up hiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like literally, sort of, running under the rock, but if you see that people might see you, you avoid being seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a deer, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like... You know, there's that sutra where the Buddha reaffirmed Ananda because they were sewing the robes with a katina.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was just, you know, a monastery full of monks and many of them were probably sotāpānas, sakadāgāmīs, you know, which means relatively accomplished.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what they were doing, they were socializing on account of a, you know, noble cause of sewing the robes, you know, for the auspicious gathering of the kathina.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the Buddha came in, he was like, what is this noise?
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought it was a band of fishermen in here.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, oh Lord, we're getting ready, we're sewing the robes, and then he just blasted it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you still have work to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should stop wasting your time with these distractions and basically go to solitude and practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can sort of say that, oh, yeah, you went to a forest or somebody went to a forest for conceited reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But going to the forest is never a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sooner or later, their reasons will become clear to them, which is
[SPEAKER_00]: The point when they would either leave the forest, or leave those reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see that first-hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: When new people come in a day, and they leave the teacher right away, because they want to go, they're just looking for... they know what they're doing, and then they spend first two years going from one place to the other place, to the other place, to the other place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feels like they tried it all, and then they disrobe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or they go straight into solitude, and then don't really know what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They went for the wrong reasons, and then that becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, if they were to stay in that solitude, well, they might go mad, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if they don't go mad, and if they don't disrobe, those reasons will... they will... they'll be forced to abandon those unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha meant by that sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if he spends his time fantasizing about sensuality, sleeping all day long in the forest, the mind will adjust.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll stop doing those things, because forest is directly counterproductive for those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He refuses to leave the solitude, refuses to disrespect the solitude, basically, in terms of his views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that contradicts it will be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other monk is the one who is not constantly thinking about spirituality, who might be quite inspiring and restrained and everything else, but he never leaves his temple, he never leaves his monastery, he never leaves the proximity of people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say people, I mean lay people and monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he talks to other followers, he encourages them... he gives talk which encourages them to stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, okay, that's... that's the political side of running the monasteries.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're not going to go into that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, I'm just saying from the practice point of view, even if you're making loads of effort towards your restraint and everything, you do have to recognize what environment you're in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is most of the day that you spend, is it with other people, including other monks?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't talk to anyone, are there other monks and lay people around you, I don't know, eight hours per day of your waking time?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it is so, it means you're not in solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you have a... you have a break in your room or something, but that's the... like a minority of your time spent in solitude, while the vast majority is just surrounded in the crowd.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the solitude in everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, people might call that sutta, well, the true solitude is the one without the greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and you'll arrive at that when you do recognize the validity of the physical solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you do that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's really, like, not that important, 90% of the suttas would not be talking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, as I said, probably quite a noble saṅgha at the time, of Aryans and so on, were together sewing the rope.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha reprimanded them for socializing in such ridiculous, pointless manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone how much more today you would have that, when it's... most of the time, it's not even for such a lofty cause of solving the road.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like just, ah, well, we're washing spittoons together, and now we're sweeping the leaves together, and now we're doing this together, and now we're together, and we're together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we go and meditate together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we go and meditate together with lay people together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we have group retreats where you can't stay in the forest alone, but you must come here, and thirty of us will sit together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we eat together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we eat breakfast together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, we do chores together.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, okay, so how many hours per day you spend together?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, those hours that you don't
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, or in your bedroom, in the shower, toilet, work, or your bedroom, which is a paper wall next to another bedroom, with another person in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're never really alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: From that point of view, you will only be emulating the ideas of solitude and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're playing in the sand, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to reiterate,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if somebody is in the solitude, avoiding socializing for unwholesome reasons, give them a year or two, those reasons will either have to change or they will leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the solitude, the eh... not socializing, well, will make it clear for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it both.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have those wrong reasons for solitude and stay in the solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality, laziness, non-diligence, not wanting to deal with people, avoiding, running away, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all going to be highlighted, and then you're either going to give in to it, and abandon the solitude, or the solitude will straighten all of those knots out for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, because this inscription of solitude here,
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't just mean freedom from greed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means the actual physical solitude.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this dhamma is for one who is content, not for one who is discontent.
[SPEAKER_01]: With reference to what was this said, here a bhikkhu is content with any kind of robes, alms food, lodgings and medicines and provisions for the sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because not being content, you could use that as a major distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: For making robes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, for making robes, for entertaining the crowds for the sake of support, because you need support for the monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, as if none of those things are related to your choices and actions you made.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even trying to get more requisites than you need involves non-solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, even like, for example, again, I'm not talking about the temples, the cultural places where people gather and do the rituals.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm talking about, say, a monastery, which is, well, at least on paper, where monks go to train and practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that is like...
[SPEAKER_00]: You shouldn't, or you can't afford to be building it for the sake of some sort of ideal of having a great monastery, where it's going to be like this, like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can only be built in response to the practical need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything else is too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means everything else would then result in you having to maintain certain level of engagement with lay people because you need a certain threshold of funds to maintain the big place that you built.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, that means that everything else becomes secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including, very often, the monk's solitude and practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh no, we all have to come and eat together because our big lay supporters, they like to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they don't like what they see, as in, they don't see any monks, they all went to their kutis, they might stop coming.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they stop coming, they'll stop making donations.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they stop making donations, well, we can't maintain all these twenty kutis that we built unnecessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's built in response to a practical need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, hopefully, with the idea of zero maintenance in the future, you don't want to rely on having to have twenty monks all the time, so you can divide all the duties and chores, so that everybody can do everything, so things can stay functional.
[SPEAKER_00]: You build simply with minimal maintenance, and then you factor in that tomorrow you might be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if now there are ten monks, tomorrow you might be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will you be able to maintain all this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can't, you shouldn't be going forward, if you're looking to how, sort of, establish a place for proper practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're looking how to establish institution, which is already a temple, even if you call it a forest monastery, well, that's a different... that's a different ballgame, but that's... that's not something that a forest monk or somebody who wants to practice the dhamma should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're also being able to
[SPEAKER_01]: Get, you know, get robes, alms food, medicines, shelters, to sort those things out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all needed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something we all agree in the Upasampada procedure.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the basis that I agree to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything over that is extra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything else over that is unnecessary, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I just want a different kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: But being able to sort... Are you recording, by the way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The time's going down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be able to get those things and be content with the simple things, you know, being able to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Organize shelter for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Know how to get alms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Know how to fast.
[SPEAKER_01]: Know how to deal with the body when it's sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: What medicines to use.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to sew your clothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need that many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what nisaya should be all about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, you teach them in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on top of that, you literally equip them so that they can live alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can live independently.
[SPEAKER_00]: They'll know how to look after themselves in that basic survival manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you live in the forest, you cut, you fall, you smash your elbow, twist your ankle, or have basic recognition like, oh, hold on, am I sick?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just knowing certain practical things how to survive.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you prepare that with dumb understanding, then yeah, you can go and live anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that gives you, you know, being able to survive by yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it gives you the confidence, contentment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, content, and that's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another thing is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimately, the dhamma is that which makes you content, even if you don't have the basic requisites that you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't threaten your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get sick, prospect of severe illness, maybe death, you don't go distraught.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you've been practicing dhamma, you won't be able to be distraught.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, you'll seek out the medicine, but not at all cost.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could see that there were cases of monks who spent 20-30 years in the forest, in the jungle, and then they got sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, they needed to stay in the hospital for the sake of, basically, staying alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even that, that's not something they wanted to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't want to stay in hospital.
[SPEAKER_00]: The bare minimum, just to be repaired, and they went back into the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what you value, that's what you got used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But many people today act out of life is the greatest gain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else is worth doing if it sort of even exposes a bit of a bit of risk to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can live your lay life like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as a monk, that's kind of completely counterproductive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let alone spending your time worrying about your future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Building a monk's hospital and what...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's nice if lay people do it for whatever purpose, but if you're doing it out of your own existential concern, oh, what am I going to do when I get old, if I get sick?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you should have thought about it when you haven't been practicing, because arahant cannot possibly worry about those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, even anāgāmī, for goodness sake, can't worry about those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even sotāpanna can't worry about those things to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even for people who are, for example, live outdoors, and have, you know, survival skills, even they, to an extent, do not worry about old age.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because...
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been surviving by themselves their whole lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many examples of people living out in the woods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, not necessarily, yeah, exactly, not necessarily monks or religious people, just in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, you see, it's quite, it's quite a feat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's quite inspiring to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that level of independence, even in a, like, completely, again, not following Buddha's teaching or whatever, but just live simply, remotely, roughly,
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's perfectly fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even when he isn't fine, he's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's still not... not the... not the... not the reason, not the cause for giving it all up and running back into the crowd where people look after you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's... the life is not going to last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you live a hundred years, it's not long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your mind is bent on sensuality, if your mind is bent on comfort and avoiding pain,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is better to live a shorter life with a greater quality to it, quality in terms of practicing the dhamma and dedication towards that, even if sometimes compromises your health or exposes you to some risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do it foolishly or crazily, like in the suttas, you don't go and stand in front of a mad elephant or something like that, but you certainly don't stay in a little village house because, you know, you might get sick in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can stay if you don't want to practice dhamma, sure, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, why are you a monk in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, I'm coming from, obviously, the Western point of view, where we are not brought up as Buddhists.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes people in Asian countries are ordained for traditional reasons, act like priests and stuff, and that's absolutely fine, if that's what they do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm talking about somebody who does ordain,
[SPEAKER_00]: Coming from a completely different culture, so there's absolutely no traditional value for any of the Westerners to be a Buddhist monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means they ordain out of some sort of inspiration based on the Buddha's teaching, based on the suttas that they read, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't then commit yourself to it, and set yourself, and expose yourself to some risk or something, well, you will never gonna learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're never gonna learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sort of follows into the next... this dhamma is for one who's energetic, not for one who's lazy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, Bhikkhu has aroused energy for abandoning unwholesome qualities and acquiring wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is strong, firm in exertion, not casting off the duty of cultivating wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the dhamma is for one who's not doing... becoming a monk out of tradition, because... Out of duty or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think that might have been the case back in the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, dhamma is for one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and obviously that's the reason one should do it, but I think today, Buddhism being quite a major religion part of society, I think that many other reasons people would ordain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not really talking about every single person who wears robes, but I'm like somebody who did ordain for relatively non-traditional reasons to practice the dhamma, and then doesn't practice it by staying
[SPEAKER_00]: Dependent on the crowd, dependent on the establishment, worrying about the future, worrying about what I'll do when I get old, if I can't climb the hill or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, instead of worrying about that, practice now, because the Buddha would say himself so many times, practice now while you can, otherwise it will be too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you practice now, you won't be worried about later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the the case of Mahārāja Mahākassava, where the Buddha saw him in the forest, wearing hemp robes and living quite a hard ascetic life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, oh, come on, you finish your work, come and stay with me, I get plenty of offers of better dwellings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're old, you don't need to endure that pain anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, well, it's not painful, because I've done all the work, I develop my mind in jhānas, I can develop them at will, establish them at will.
[SPEAKER_00]: All this is pure joy, and then the Buddha praised that, and inferred that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said that would be the inspiration for future generations, hearing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not advocating carelessness,
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm not certainly...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not endorsing cowardice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cowardice.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you realize there's nothing careless about seeking solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, it can be quite a frightening thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's not like a physical existential threat, people would be afraid of being alone, not having anything to do, not having duties dictating their day, what I must do, not having other people telling them what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's the most frightening thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: For most people, well, for any other enlightened mind, and so not becoming a monk, on one hand, and then not dealing with it on the other, well, it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: As somebody who's inspired to practice dhamma, that's the ultimate thing you need to deal with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandoning your own sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot do that for as long as you're in the crowd.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say crowd, I don't mean you sit in the middle of Times Square or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean crowded with other monks constantly, with other lay people, with other people, full stop.